Okay בוקר טוב boker tov today's דף daf is מח mem chet
בבא בתרא Bava Batra 48, a nice beautiful self-contained סוגיא sugya about
תלוה וזבין, taluve vezavin, forcing somebody to make a sale and we
actually started it yesterday but just to have the entirety of the
סוגיא sugya we'll pick back from double back to the bottom of
מז mem zayin עמוד ב amud bet and we'll start with אמר
רב הונא. Amar Rav Huna. So we had just been teaching in
yesterday's דף daf that if a גזלן gazlan brings evidence that he
purchased a field and a signed שטר, shtar, it's not valid because
we assume that the person agreed to writing the שטר shtar only
because he was afraid of the consequences of what would happen if
he would not do that. And now we're going to take a
look about how that fits into a general principle about somebody who
is forced into a sale. So let's take a look. The גמרא
Gemara says like
this. אמר
רב הונא,
Amar Rav
Huna, so it's like five lines from the bottom on מז mem
zayin עמוד ב, amud bet, says רב הונא, Rav Huna, תלוה וזבין
זביניה זביני taluve vezavin zevineih zevinei if somebody suspended somebody, compelled somebody
and he sold his field or he sold something, it's a legitimate
sale. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? What's the reason? כל דמזבין איניש אי
לאו דאניס לא הוה מזבין. kol demazbin inish ee lav de-anis lo
hava mazbin. Anything that people sell, if they were not forced to
do it they would not sell. Now that obviously reflects a time
when you're not living in a commercial economy and you're living in
basically an agricultural society and therefore people don't make money by selling
things, they make money by working the land and they only buy
things that they need and they only sell things when they actually
need to raise the funds, so they do it out of a
sense of pressure and not because they really want to be doing
it. So anytime people will sell things, or at least some of
the times people sell things, it's because circumstances are forcing them to
do so and even though they're compelled by circumstances, that doesn't mean
that at the end of the day when whatever the outside factors
are they make a decision that they want to be selling something
then that's the decision they're making, that's the decision that they've come
to and therefore they are willing it and want it to be
valid and therefore it's a good sale. So here too, just because
somebody is holding a gun to your head, at the end of
the day you're selling it because you don't want to get shot.
So how is that different than selling it because you don't want
your family to starve because you don't have enough money? Now there
obviously is a difference which the גמרא Gemara immediately says. So let's
take a look. The גמרא Gemara says ודילמא, v'dilma, maybe two lines
from the bottom of מז mem zayin עמוד ב, amud bet, ודילמא
שאני אונסא דנפשיה מאונסא דאחרינא, v'dilma shani unsa denafshei me-unsa de-achrinei,
maybe it's different when it's your yourself dealing and making a decision
based on the different factors that are at play and the different
sense of pressures that you're under and demands that you're under and
at the end of the day you're the author of your own
decision. I can decide whether to let my family go hungry or
whether I'm going to sell this thing and in the end I
own that decision, it's my decision. If somebody is forcing their will
upon me and holding a gun to a head, then it's really
not my decision, it is really that the decision is being forced
upon me and that could obviously make a major difference. That makes
an enormous amount of sense. So let's take a look what the
גמרא Gemara says.
The גמרא Gemara says like this.
אלא, ela, so you're right, the גמרא Gemara says we can't just
prove it from a normal case of sale. That's not a good
enough example. We have to look at something that when you're forced
by outside factors. So כדתניא kidtanya we'll try to bring it from
the following proof, top of מח mem chet עמוד
א, amud aleph, יקריב אותו, yakriv oto, this is by a קרבן.
korban. It says that when a person brings an עולה, olah, יקריב
אותו yakriv oto he should bring it. מלמד שכופין אותו, melamed shekofin
oto, יקריב אותו yakriv oto is being read not just the man
should bring the קרבן korban that he vowed, but we בית דין
beis din should compel him to bring it. So if somebody took
a vow for a קרבן korban he needs to be compelled to
bring it. יכול בעל כרחו, yakol be'al korcho,
maybe even if it is compelled under compulsion against his will? תלמוד
לומר לרצונו, talmud lomar lirtzono, יקריב אותו לרצונו yakriv oto lirtzono
it has to be his will, his desire. הא כיצד? ha katzad?
So how do you balance that that you can force somebody and
it can be their desire? כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה אני. kofin
oto ad sheyomar rotzeh ani. So this tells you that you can
force him and if in the end he says yes I will
it, I desire it, then that's good. So even though he's being
forced by outside, if in the end he desires it and he
says the words רוצה אני, rotzeh ani, we'll get back to that
in a minute, then that shows that it is a good sale.
So here too if somebody is forced to make a sale in
the end it would be a good sale. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, you can't compare those cases. ודילמא שאני התם דניחא
ליה דתהוי ליה כפרה, v'dilma shani hasam denichla lei d'teihavei lei kaparah,
maybe that case is different, maybe that case he actually wants the
atonement that the קרבן korban brings, there's something something that he's getting
out of it and that's why, and it's different than like in
this other case. Now, of course you could say maybe he wants
the money of the sale, and we're going to see, we haven't
alluded to it before and we're going to continue to, we're going
to return to it, that all of this is case of תלוהו
וזבין taluhu ve-zavin *taluvei vezavin* when he makes a sale, not תלוהו
ויהיב *taluvei vehayiv* if he gives a gift. There has to be
something in the end that we could say he made his peace
with it, because at least he was getting paid for it. So
there's some degree of an exchange and therefore even though there's a
compulsion, we could say, okay, he was compelled, but at the end
he made he decided to go through with it. Look, he was
getting paid, so so in the end we'll believe that he actually
wanted it to happen. Okay, so the idea that he gets a
כפרה *kapara* for his קרבן korban *korban* is not exactly logically necessarily
different than the idea of that you get money when you sell
something. Why would that make that case special? It could be that
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying is that he took a
vow. Nobody obligated him to take a vow. He took a vow
that he wanted to do it. So he expressed his desire originally
that he wanted the כפרה *kapara* what the קרבן korban *korban* would
bring. And now we are just sort of reconnecting him to that
desire. It's not something that we're totally externally forcing on him. It's
something that he took upon himself. Alright, so we'll get back to
that. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* also has another particular take on that, but
but
that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, maybe that case is different.
If you look at the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*, דהוי ליה כפרה וכי
אמר רוצה אני rotzeh ani ודאי בלב שלם קאמר *dehavei lei kapara
vechi amar rotze ani vadai belev shalem ka'amar*. Again, maybe it's also
a point that כפרה *kapara* is different than just money. Since you're
getting this religious benefit of כפרה *kapara*, maybe there deep down it's
something you want. So that case is special let's say. כפרה *kapara*
is more worth more than money. You'll finally that'll make you come
to peace with the decision. You really do want it, or you
accepted it upon yourself to begin with. And we'll get back in
a minute to a point that תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* makes about this
and the next case. So let's see the next case. So you
can't prove it from there. That's different than just forcing a sale
on someone. ואלא מסיפא *Ve'ela meseifa* from the second case. וכן אתה
אומר *Vechein ata omer* from this משנה Mishna *Mishna*. בגיטי נשים *Begitei
nashim*, the same is true by a גט get *get* for a
woman. It says גיטי נשים *gitei nashim* because גט get? *get* could
just mean a document. Okay, by a גט get *get*, כופין אותו
עד ad, שיאמר רוצה אני rotzeh ani, *kofin oso ad sheyomar rotze
ani*. If the husband, it's a situation where he's obligated to divorce
his wife, then בית דין Beis Din. *Beis Din* and he doesn't
want, but still he has to be the one issuing the divorce.
בית דין Beis Din. *Beis Din* can't issue the divorce. So בית
דין *Beis Din* will compel him until he again says these words
רוצה אני rotzeh ani *rotze ani*. So you see that that works.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ודילמא שאני התם *Vedilma shani
hasam*. Wait, maybe that's different. דמצוה לשמוע דברי חכמים *demitzvah lishmoa divrei
chachamim*. Because maybe since חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* have determined that you're obligated
to divorce your wife, your רוצה אני *rotze ani* is coming, this
is sort of similar to the idea of דהוי ליה כפרה *dehavei
lei kapara*. There's some religious component here that even that okay there
is a compulsion, you are being compelled I should say. It is
being forced on you, but when you say רוצה אני *rotze ani*
it could be that you really mean it. Because at the end
of the day you you know you want to do the religiously
right thing, you want to do the כפרה *kapara*, you want to
do the right thing, you want to listen to the חכמים *Chachamim*.
There are people that are saying that this is the right thing
to do. Okay, and you want to align yourself with that. So
we're more prepared to say that you really do make your peace
with it. However, that is not like our case where it's a
completely secular matter and just because you're being compelled does not mean
that you've actually made your peace with it. Now I want to
pause here for a second to focus both on the רוצה אני
*rotze ani* and on the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is bringing
this as evidence. Because as I said, you know, the cases in
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* are only cases where money is being given.
It didn't say that explicitly before. It did say זבין *zavin* sale
not יהיב *yahiv*. It is going to be more explicit later on.
You know, but we need the case where you're actually getting money
in exchange and we could say that you did make your peace
with it once you were being compelled. I should also just mention
for those that are being bothered by this whole idea that even
something that is under coerced, I mean I think that was the
better word I was looking for than compelled. Even something that is
coerced can be valid if you take the money. We'll see in
the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* might want to limit it in
ways in which you demonstrated that you did make a choice about
it, could be one of the reasons we're also saying that's true.
We're also going to find out there's ways that you could issue
a מודעא mudaa. *modaa*, a statement in advance that makes a declaration
that you are being compelled and that you're being coerced, excuse me,
and that nullifies it. So it's not that this is totally given
to abuse, which one might you might be concerned about. But nevertheless,
okay, we are limiting ourselves to a case where even with the
coercion you're getting money. The problem here is, and there's therefore some
type of an exchange. The problem is how these cases about the
קרבן *korban* and the divorce, you're not getting anything in exchange. So
wouldn't this be an evidence that you this would apply even in
a case where there's no money being given? Even in a case
if you're being coerced to make a gift? So as I said
by the case of the divorce you could say by the case
of the קרבן *korban* you could say. Look, you are getting atonement
and that's a type of that's what you're getting for your קרבן
and so that's certain and maybe it's even better than money as
the גמרא Gemara indicated. But what about the case of the divorce
of the wife? What do you get in
exchange for divorcing your wife? So רשב"ם Rashbam says, well, you don't
have to pay her support. It's not exactly the same. So תוספות
Tosafos has a better answer, and if you take a look at
תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos says the following.
He says ותרץ ר"י, ve-tieretz Ri, this is the תוספות אילימא Tosafos
i-leima at the end of that תוספות, Tosafos, the first תוספות Tosafot
on the דף, daf, דכל דבר שהוא מחויב לעשות הוי כמו מכר.
de-chol davar she-hu mechuyav la'asos, havei k'mo mecher.
Anything you're obligated to do is like a sale. והכא הרי הוא
מחויב להביא קרבן ולקמן נמי מחויב הוא לגרש את אשתו. ve-hacha harei
hu mechuyav le-havi korban u-lekaman nami mechuyav hu le-garesh es ishto. Okay,
so therefore he says look, it doesn't have to be you're getting
something in exchange. The point is you're making your peace with it
even though you're being coerced. So when it's a sale, what's allowing
you to make your peace with it is that you're at least
getting your compensation for it. By things that you're obligated to do,
what's making you make your peace with it is that you actually
are doing what you are obligated. And therefore it's not like somebody's
forcing something external on you as we mentioned in the case of
the קרבן you even started by accepting it on yourself. So that
the גמרא Gemara feels is analogous. If you're being coerced and it's
not just giving up something out of the blue, you're either getting
compensated for it like תלוהו וזבין taluhu ve-zavin. or you're doing something
that you should be doing anyway, in those cases we'll say that
combined with the coercion you have made your peace with it and
that would be valid. That's the analogy that is being made. Although
the גמרא Gemara says again that maybe the קרבן and the גט
get, are even beyond that, not just you're obligated but you're obligated
somewhat like religiously and therefore you can't compare to the case where
there's no obligation and you're just being compensated. Okay, so we still
don't have a proof directly to our case of תלוהו וזבין. taluhu
ve-zavin Now one more point before going forward, I can't resist but
reading רמב"ם Rambam what רמב"ם Rambam says about this. Because רמב"ם Rambam
discusses where is this idea
that how could you say רוצה אני if you're being forced in
the case of גט? get And רמב"ם Rambam basically makes the point
about תוספות, Tosafot you're obligated to do it and the point of
the גמרא Gemara even more than that, מצוה לשמוע דברי חכמים, mitzvah
lismoa divrei chachamim, that that helps us say that this is something
that you really want. Okay and here's what רמב"ם Rambam says about
this. Let me just find this.
רמב"ם Rambam says the following.
Okay
so רמב"ם Rambam says the following: מי שדינו נותן שכופין אותו לגרש
את אשתו, mi she-dino noten she-kofin oso le-garesh es ishto, this is
גירושין ב כ, Gerushin bet chaf, ולא רצה לגרש, ve-lo ratza le-garesh,
he's obligated. בית דין של ישראל בכל מקום ובכל זמן מכין אותו
עד שיאמר רוצה אני. beis din shel Yisrael be-chol makom u-ve-chol zman
makim oso ad she-yomar rotzeh ani. They beat him up until he
says רוצה אני, I want it. Okay and then he goes on
with a non-Jew which we'll get to in the גמרא. Gemara And
then he says like this: ולמה לא בטל גט זה שהרי הוא
אנוס בין ביד עכו"ם בין ביד ישראל? ve-lamah lo batel get zeh
she-harei hu anus bein be-yad akum bein be-yad Yisrael? Why isn't the
גט get, nullified? He's forced, it's not out of his will. שאין
אומרים אנוס אלא למי שנלחץ ונדחק לעשות דבר שאינו מחויב בו מן
התורה. she-ein omrim anus ela le-mi she-neilchatz ve-nidechak la'asos davar she-eino mechuyav
bo min ha-Torah.
You only say forced if you're being coerced to do something that
you're not obligated מן התורה. min ha-Torah. So then it's completely an
external coercion, there's nothing internal that makes you the one that should
be doing it, so then it's not you doing it, it's being
coerced upon you. כגון מי שהוכה עד שמכר או שנתן ke-gon mi
she-huka ad she-machar o she-natan like somebody that was beaten up until
he sold something or gave something, which is exactly our case, right?
תלוהו וזבין ve-zavin, and he includes מכר. machar. That רמב"ם Rambam said
is a degree of coercion. אבל מי שתקפו יצרו הרע לבטל מצוה
או לעשות עבירה והוכה עד, aval mi she-takfo yitzro ha-ra le-vatel mitzvah
o la'asos aveirah ve-huka ad, but somebody whose יצר הרע yitzer hara
got the better of him לבטל מצוה le-vatel mitzvah to go against
a מצוה mitzvah או לעשות עבירה o la'asos aveirah to do a
sin,
and he was beaten עד,
excuse me I lost my place, עד שעשה דבר שחייב לעשותו או
שנתרחק מדבר אסור לעשותו
ad she-asa davar she-chayav la'asoso
o she-nisrachak mi-davar asur la'asoso
and he's beaten until in the end he does something that he's
obligated to do
or he distances himself from something he wasn't supposed to do. So
you basically beat him up until he aligned his actions with what
he is religiously obligated to do or not do. אין זה אנוס
ממנו. ein zeh anus mimenu. You're not forcing him, you're not coercing
him. אלא הוא אנס עצמו בדעתו הרעה. ela hu anas atzmo be-da'ato
ha-ra'ah. He had been coercing himself to go against what his deep
יצר הטוב yitzer hatov really wanted him. It's an interesting way of
looking at ourselves and our will. Deep down we want to do
the right thing, my יצר הרע yitzer hara is getting the better
of me, and you're beating my יצר הרע yitzer hara out of
me. לפיכך זה שאינו רוצה לגרש מאחר שהוא רוצה להיות מישראל, lefi-kach
zeh she-eino rotzeh le-garesh me-achar she-hu rotzeh lihyos mi-Yisrael, this man who
doesn't want to divorce since he wants to be part of the
Jewish people, רוצה לעשות כל המצוות ולהתרחק מן העבירות, rotzeh la'asos kol
ha-mitzvos u-le-hisrachek min ha-aveiros, and ויצרו הוא שתקפו, ve-yitzro hu she-takfo,
it's only my evil inclination that has seized me. וכיון שהוכה עד
שתשש יצרו. ve-keivan שהוכה עד שתשש יצרו she-huka ad she-tashash yitzro. And
I was beaten until my יצר הרע *yetzer hara* was weakened, and
רוצה אני *rotzeh ani*, then כבר גירש לרצונו *kvar garesh lirtzono*, then
I am ultimately you're freeing me. It's sort of like פרעה *Paroh*,
right, that everybody asks why could Hashem harden the heart of פרעה
*Paroh*? So some answer is he was hardening him enough to withstand
the pressure of the מכות *makkot* so that he was able to
do what his heart really wanted. Okay, so here too you're sort
of beating out something a little bit the reverse I guess. You're
beating out the יצר הרע *yetzer hara* so I can free my
יצר הטוב *yetzer hatov* to do what it really wants. Anyway, a
very, you know, graphic sort of description from רמב"ם Rambam, *Rambam*, but
that's the idea that when I'm obligated, certainly religiously obligated, and then
you're coercing me, we can say in the end I am doing
it freely of my will. I should say one other thing before
we continue, which is the phrase of רוצה אני *rotzeh ani*. The
phrase of רוצה אני *rotzeh ani* appears only by קרבן *korban* and
by גט get. *get*, and it doesn't appear by the cases of
when you're coercing somebody to sell his property. In those cases, when
we're saying it's valid, you have to say רוצה אני *rotzeh ani*?
So, you know, רמב"ם *Rambam* does not say that, but ראב"ד *Ra'avad*
says in the case of קרבן *korban* and גט *get* רמב"ם *Rambam*
says רוצה אני *rotzeh ani*, but in the case of sales רמב"ם
*Rambam* does not say it, ראב"ד *Ra'avad* sort of inserts it. So
that's interesting. Do you need him to specifically articulate and own the
responsibility of the decision by saying רוצה אני *rotzeh ani* or not?
So you can understand sort of saying you do need it across
the board. But what would רמב"ם *Rambam*'s reason be to say you
need it by גט *get* and by קרבן *korban* which is really
the only cases the sources say it and not by the monetary
issues and by the sale? And here there could be a difference
between desire and like will. You know, I want to, you know,
I am agreeing to do it. Do I really want to do
it? No. You know, do I really want to sell my beautiful
car? No, but I have to put food on the table. So
it's not coming from a deep sense of, you know, of desire,
but I am committing and agreeing to go through with it. I
have decided to do it even though I don't really want to
do it. So רמב"ם *Rambam* indicates that by, you know, by the
קרבן *korban* it says לרצונו *lirtzono*. You have to really wish it
and want it and desire it, okay? And therefore you might have
to say רוצה אני *rotzeh ani*. It's not just I'm agreeing but
I desire to do it. And by the גט *get* as well,
רמב"ם *Rambam* says one of the first of ten requirements רמב"ם *Rambam*
says is in the תורה Torah *Torah* for a גט *get* is
that the husband has to be מגרש לרצונו *megaresh lirtzono* because it
says ואם לא תמצא חן בעיניו *ve'im lo timtza chen be'einav*, he
doesn't desire his wife. Okay, and the אחרונים *acharonim* ask, I mean
every transaction has to be לדעתו *leda'ato*, you have to be committing
and willing to do it. Okay, but the difference that רמב"ם *Rambam*
is adding here, it's not enough to agree to do it, you
have to really desire it. So it could be specifically by גט
*get* and by קרבן *korban* there has to be not just an
agreement but a desire and you have to actually say רוצה אני
*rotzeh ani*. All right, sorry, I couldn't resist. Anyway, so that's what
we have it. The case of גט *get* and קרבן *korban* you,
a, they also say רוצה אני *rotzeh ani*, you know, which might
be unique to that. But anyway, you can't bring a proof from
it because there there's a particular obligation and a religious obligation. So
how do we know in our case by selling the field that
that will work? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, אלא
סברא הוא *ela sevara hu*. Okay, fine, it's a סברא *sevara*. אגב
אונסיה גמר ומקני agav ontzei gamar umakni. *agav unseih gamar umakni*. You'll
just
basically I can't prove it from anything and I can't make it
analogous to case of like outside circumstances because in the end I'm
owning the decision. So even though yes I am being coerced, it's
just a סברא *sevara* to say that even with that coercion, you
know, I in the end I am choosing, not necessarily wishing it,
desiring it, but I am agreeing and I am choosing to go
through with it and making my peace with it because that at
least will get the guy to stop holding the gun to my
head. All right, now you could still say you know legally we
as the בית דין *Beis Din* shouldn't recognize the legitimacy of that
and this all seems unfair. As I said, we'll get to cases
that try to limit this. All right, and we'll see there are
opinions that don't agree with this. Okay, but that's the argument, that's
the basis of רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna*'s statement that תליוהו
וזבין זביניה זבינא tulyuhu ve'zavin zevinei zevina *talyuhu vezavin zivinei zivina*. Okay,
מותיב רב יהודה *motiv Rav Yehuda*. רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* challenged this.
גט המעושה בישראל כשר kasher. *get hame'useh b'Yisrael kasher*, if a גט
*get* is coerced by the Jewish court it's kosher like we said.
ובעכו"ם פסול *u've'akum pasul*, but if it's non-Jews coerce it, even a
גט *get* that you're obligated that בית דין *Beis Din* has decided
you're obligated to give, if it's done through non-Jews, you know, these
like the people would hire these squads to beat up somebody to
give a גט *get*, that's invalid. ובעכו"ם *u've'akum*, but you can be
valid through non-Jews, חובטין אותו ואומרים לו עשה מה שישראל אומר לך
*chovtin oso ve'omrin lo asei mah she'Yisrael omer lach*. If they beat
the guy and say do what the Jewish בית דין *Beis Din*
tells you, then it is valid, then they're an arm of בית
דין *Beis Din*. All right, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands that
all of these are cases where, way תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* explains it,
the ראשונים *Rishonim* explain it, where it's the same case, you're obligated
to give a גט *get*. So but if the בית דין *Beis
Din* does it or the בית דין *Beis Din* uses the non-Jew
it's valid, but if the non-Jews act on their own to coerce
it it's not valid. Why not? It's a case that he's obligated,
he presumably says רוצה אני, who should care who is the one
doing it? So ואמאי Ve'amai התם נמי נימא hasam nami neima גב
gav אגב אונסיה גמר ומגרש. agav ontzei gamar umagarish.
Let's say because of the compulsion he in the end, you know,
decides to give the גט, he makes up his mind, he he,
you know, he he, you know, he comes to peace with the
decision.
So גמרא Gemara says no, האי אתמר עלה Hai itmar alah אמר
רב משרשיא Amar Rav Mesharshaya דבר תורה Devar Torah אפילו בעכו"ם afillu
be'akum כשר. kosher, You're right, because really מדאורייתא mide'oraisa even through a
non-Jew it's כשר, even if they don't say that do it because
of the Jewish בית דין. Even if they're not operating as an
arm of בית דין. If it's somebody who's obligated to give a
גט and these non-Jews are beating him up and in the end
he says רוצה אני and he gives it, then he's made his,
you know, he's come to terms with it, he's made his peace
with it, it's good, אגב אונסיה agav ontzei גמר ומגרש. gamar umagarish.
ומה טעם אמרו בעכו"ם פסול u'mah ta'am amru be'akum pasul
so why do they say it's not valid by a non-Jew? כדי
שלא תהא כל אחת ואחת הולכת ותולה עצמה ביד עכו"ם ומפקעת עצמה
מיד בעלה. kedei shelo tehei kol achas ve'achas holeches vesolah atzmah beyad
akum umafka'as atzmah miyad ba'alah. Because then you're going to have women
hiring goon squads and they're going to go ahead and hire these
non-Jews to do it and if they can even operate independently and
can generate a good גט, and therefore that is not a situation
that we want. Obviously this raises all the problems of the עגונה
agunah issue, which are, you know, not directly our focus. I will
say though, again underscore, that this is only when he is obligated
to give a גט. This would not work when he's not obligated,
that's the point that we made before, מצוה לשמוע דברי חכמים, mitzvah
lishmo'a divrei chachamim, you know, there has to be something that it's
not just the coercion, but something that makes it he can reconcile
himself that this is what he wants to do. He's getting money,
he's obligated to do it anyway, and so on. Okay, ומפקעת עצמה
מיד
בעלה. Umafka'as atzmah miyad ba'alah. מתיב רב המנונא. Masiv Rav Hamnuna. רב
המנונא Rav Hamnuna challenged, and this was the גמרא Gemara we saw
before from the משנה Mishna in גיטין, Gittin, לקח מסיקריקון וחזר ולקח
מבעל הבית. Lakach misikrikon vechazar velakach miba'al habayis. So this person bought
a field from first the non-Jewish the סיקריקון sikrikon who, you know,
stole these fields, the strongman, and then he went and he redid
a and he repurchased the field from the original owner.
מקחו בטל. mikcho batul. It's not valid even though the original obviously
it's not valid from the סיקריקון, sikrikon, the סיקריקון sikrikon doesn't legitimately
own it. But then he went back and he bought it from
the original owner. Now the original owner is selling it to him
because he's got very few choices. His field was already stolen by
this סיקריקון, sikrikon, might as well sell it to this other Jew
and get some money from it. But okay, so fine, those are
circumstances that are coercing him. Maybe the סיקריקון sikrikon himself is going
to, you know, there's an implicit threat that he that this original
owner has to go along with it. But all those cases should
still make it valid, it's תלויה וזבין זביניה זבינא. teluya vezavin zivinei
zivina. So why is it not valid? ואמאי, Ve'amai,
why is that not valid? התם נמי אגב אונסיה גמר ומקני, hasam
nami agav ontzei gamar umakni, because of the coercion of the circumstances,
of the סיקריקון, sikrikon, the original owner sold it, okay, he was
coerced but in the end he sold it, so it should be
valid. האי אתמר עלה, Hai itmar alah, no, so the answer is
it was taught that אמר רב לא שנו אלא דאמר ליה לך
חזק וקני, Amar Rav lo shanu ella de'amar lei lech chazek ukeni,
like we said yesterday, you know, you're right, it actually would work.
When do we say it doesn't work? If he only did it
verbally, he he said go ahead and, you know, take possession. אבל
בשטר קנה, Aval bishtar kana, but when he shows enough that he
really is committed to it by writing a שטר, shtar, then it
is good. So again here at least we see that it's not
just every case of coercion. There has to be money which reconciles
him to it. I mean we haven't said the money yet but
I've been saying it all along, רשב"ם's Rashbam been saying it all
along. And there has to be something that he shows he really
does mean it. If he was just going along, he would have
just said go do it verbally, he wrote a שטר, shtar, that
proves it. Of course you don't know, he could feel coerced to
write a שטר. shtar. But anyway, once there's a writing of the
שטר, shtar, that shows that there really is a reconciling and we
say אגב אונסיה גמר ומקני. gmar umakni
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, where were we? ולשמואל דאמר
אף בשטר נמי לא קנה, Ulishmuel de'amar af bishtar nami lo kana,
according to שמואל Shmuel who says that even with a שטר shtar
it's not enough unless he writes אחריות. achrayus. If he's writing אחריות
achrayus and taking liability for the sale, clearly he's showing that he
is really meaning to do the sale. But שמואל Shmuel says even
a שטר, shtar, maybe he's doing it because of the, you know,
coercion. So you see that under these circumstances of coercion it's not
good even if he goes so far to write a שטר. shtar.
So מאי איכא למימר, mai ika lemeimar, how do you reconcile that
with רב הונא's Rav Huna claim? So מודה שמואל היכא דיהיב זוזי,
modeh Shmuel heika de'yahiv zuzei, שמואל Shmuel agrees if money is given
and here we finally say what we've been saying all along, it's
תלויה וזבין teluya vezavin and תלויה ויהיב. teluya veyahiv. If he actually
has given been given money, right, then he actually, you know, will
reconcile. So the cases in the משנה in גיטין Gittin was when
the sale was made and he agreed to sell it and he
wrote the שטר, shtar, even that doesn't finalize the sale, even though
normally you don't money doesn't have to change hands to finalize a
sale. But here because of the coercion, he isn't really agreeing to
it until he actually takes the money. Only with the taking of
the money does he really reconcile himself to it. Okay, so that's
our assumption all along that there had to be money or something
comparable that allows him to reconcile himself. ולרב ביבי דמסיים בה משמיה
דרב נחמן, Ulerav Bibi demasayem bah mishmei deRav Nachman, now one more.
ולרב ביבי דמסיים בה משמיה דרב נחמן u'l'Rav Bibi d'msayim bah mishmei
d'Rav Nachman now one minute according to רב ביבי Rav Bibi that
you know ends that statement in the name of רב נחמן Rav
Nachman about this case of about like if a גזלן gazlan you
know has a שדה sadeh or has a proof or whatever that
he doesn't get to keep the land because again the person only
wrote it out of a sense of coercion and he ends that
by saying קרקע אין לו מעות יש לו karka ein lo maos
yesh lo it's true the גזלן gazlan doesn't get to keep the
man land but he gets his money back so what does that
prove meaning the case we started before earlier that said a גזלן's
gazlan שטר shtar doesn't mean anything cuz the guy who sold it
to him was coerced the key question now is was there money
or not money because according to רב הונא Rav Huna who cares
that he was coerced in the end גמר ומקני gmar umakni so
רב הונא Rav Huna would say when is a גזלן gazlan not
believed when he comes with a שטר shtar when there was no
money then he wasn't גמר ומקני okay that's when we said earlier
that the שטר shtar of a גזלן gazlan is no good but
if a גזלן gazlan not only has a שטר shtar but the
money changed hands then actually it would be good okay fine so
we could say that that statement before that a גזלן gazlan you
know שטר shtar doesn't work was when money did not change hands
but we now have this statement of רב ביבי Rav Bibi who
says that that שטר shtar of a גזלן gazlan doesn't work even
after money change hands he shows the שטר shtar we don't recognize
the שטר shtar sorry you can't keep the land but מעות יש
לו maos yesh lo you get your money back so רב ביבי
Rav Bibi is saying that that שטר shtar of a גזלן gazlan
doesn't work even when money has been paid and that's why you
have to give the גזלן gazlan his money back cuz we're not
letting the sale be valid so if that's true he clearly doesn't
agree with רב הונא Rav Huna he says that when there's coercion
even when money changes hands the sale is no good so the
גמרא Gemara says so how do you deal with that so the
גמרא Gemara says רב ביבי מימרא הוא מימרא דרב הונא לא סבירא
ליה Rav Bibi memra hu memra d'Rav Huna lo svira lei yeah
רב ביבי Rav Bibi is an amoraic statement and רב הונא Rav
Huna doesn't have to agree with it you know so therefore you
know it's some statement he had he was quoting in the name
of others and therefore it's not tanaaitic it's not a problem to
רב הונא Rav Huna so what do we have now we have
that statements that sale will be good when you go to the
point of either writing a שטר shtar or receiving money we seem
to be settling on the idea of like receiving money that then
even if you're coerced it's good even outside coercion either that or
other cases where there's something that's reconciling you like you're obligated to
do it but there is a contrary voice that says even after
you received money any coercion is no good which is I think
maybe what we would have liked to see okay but that's the
position of רב הונא Rav Huna and we actually hold like רב
הונא Rav Huna that when money changes hands it is valid
and now let's take a look though at the גמרא Gemara. introduces
some possible qualifications okay אמר רבא הלכתא תליוהו וזבין זביניה זביני Amar
Rava hilchasa telyuhu vezavin zivinei zivinei
so that's the way we rule like רב הונא Rav Huna if
the somebody was suspended coerced and he sold it's a valid sale
ולא אמרן אלא v'lo amran ela now we're going to try to
give some qualifications אלא בשדה סתם ela besadeh stam
that's only when the guy said sell me one of your fields
and then you went and you picked which field so since you
were playing an active choosing role and deciding which field then we
say that that makes it something that you're like owning the that
decision and reconciling yourself with it okay
and you know and the רשב"ם Rashbam, sort of says presumably you
sold him the worst one you'll sell him the one that you'll
be okay with selling so there at least we can say there
was a degree of really being okay with that decision of course
you might not want to sell any and you're forced to pick
one but at least that you have a degree of choice that
makes it a certain ownership of a decision that already makes it
a lot more understandable אבל בשדה זו לא aval besadeh zo lo
but if the guy says sell me this field and you have
no choice then you're just acting as a tool of the person
with the gun to your head and you really it's not your
decision at all all right that makes it a lot more understandable
now we're significantly limiting it but one minute we're not done ובשדה
זו נמי לא אמרן אלא דלא ארצי זוזי ubesadeh zo nami lo
amran ela d'lo artzei zuzei no no no even when I said
it's not good when you say שדה זו sadeh zo that's only
if you did not now here there's a very important question about
the גרסא girsa read it with our גרסא girsa that's only when
you did not count out the money before we said money had
to change hands here we're adding the factor of counting the
money אבל ארצי זוזי לא aval artzei zuzei lo if I the
guy holds a gun to your head and says sell me that
field and I'm going to give you ten thousand dollars and you
with a gun to your head you sign the שטר shtar and
sell the field and he gives you the ten thousand dollars so
since you had no choice even though money changed hands we'll say
it's not good he didn't reconcile self but if after you got
the money you counted it out to make sure there was ten
thousand dollars that's showing that you really in the end went along
with the sale wasn't like everything was just thrown on you I
mean obviously you'd like there to be more money than less money
but still you know you're not really a party to it you're
just being completely controlled by the other person all right so if
you have a degree of choice or you show a degree of
will like an acquiescence either by choosing which field or even if
you don't get to choose by counting out the money. Then, then
it's going to be
good sale. והא רצי זוזי לא v'ha ratzei zuzei lo ולא אמרן
אלא דהוה ליה לאשתמוטי v'lo amran ela d'hava lei l'ishtamutei and
also even if you didn't count out the money, we only say
that it's
invalid—the guy's holding a gun to your head, you have no choice,
he threw the money in front of you but you didn't count
it
out—so that case we should say is invalid, there's nothing that shows
you reconciled yourself. Even that will only be invalid if you had
no way of escaping this, you know, you didn't have some type
of an excuse you could have used, some type of a way
you could have gotten out of it. You sort of resigned yourself
to it and went along. אבל הוה ליה לאשתמוטי, aval hava lei
l'ishtamutei, if you had, I'm sorry, so if you had no way
to get out of it, then you're completely being manipulated. But if
you had a way to get out of it and you didn't
opt that, right? You could have made up an excuse, you could
have said give me more time, you could have said something and
you clearly weren't trying and making the effort to get out of
it, so that shows that you had resigned yourself to it and
you were agreeing to it. אלא דהוה ליה לאשתמוטי לא. ela d'hava
lei l'ishtamutei lo. Okay, so now at least we have, you know,
in the end it did not limit it too much, okay, but
at least said that there's one case which it wouldn't work. You're
told שדה זו, sadeh zo, you have no choice which field, you
don't count the money, and you had no other options that you
could have availed yourself of, so, you know, I'm sorry, is that
right? And yes, and you had no other options. With those three
combined, we'll say then you were just being totally manipulated. But if
you picked the field, or you counted the money, or you didn't
bother trying some available option, all of that will show that you
reconciled yourself to the situation. All right, those things sort of make
sense and at least it makes it a little more palatable what
we were saying before, that there's some evidence that you reconciled yourself
to the situation. But now the גמרא Gemara concludes the following and
says the following: והלכתא—but v'hilchata the הלכה halacha actually
is—בכולהו דהוי זביניה זביני. b'kulhu d'hava zvineih zvini. In everything it's still
a good sale, even if it's a case of שדה זו sadeh
zo and you didn't count the money and you had no other
options, in all of those things it's always going to be a
good sale. ואפילו בשדה זו, v'afilu b'sadeh zo, even the case of
שדה זו. sadeh zo. How do you know that? דאישה כשדה זו
דמי, d'ishah k'sadeh zo dami,
because a case of a woman, we'll see in a case of
a marriage which רב אשי Rav Ashi says, is like a case
of שדה זו. sadeh zo. Okay. ואמר מימר תליוה וקידש קידושיו קידושין.
v'amar Meimar talyuha v'kadesh kidushav kidushin. If a man held a gun,
shotgun wedding—except here it's in the other direction—a man held a gun
to a woman's head and said accept this קידושין kidushin and she
accepted it—so we're going to have a contrary opinion in a second,
but right now we're saying the קידושין kidushin is valid. That's a
case of being compelled and agreeing and קידושיו קידושין. kidushav kidushin. Now
in this case the woman
is
sort of like the seller, as it were. She's agreeing to give
up herself to marry this guy. The man is quote unquote buying
her, giving the money, he's taking her. So he only wants this
woman; it's שדה זו. sadeh zo. She has no choice. She's not
said, you can either marry yourself to me or marry your sister
to me. She's only being told marry yourself to me. And nevertheless
the teaching is that it's valid, so it shows you even by
שדה זו sadeh zo it's going to be valid. And we didn't
say, you know, nobody limited it to a case that she could
have gotten out of it or nobody limited it to a case
where she counted the money. It seems like even if she can't
get out of it, even if she didn't count the money—I mean,
and the money's really
symbolic—you know, it's going to be valid. So even though the גמרא
Gemara tried to give a way in which תליוהו וזבין talyuhu v'zavin
could be more palatable because there's something to show that you're sort
of, you know, had made your peace and are going along with
it, it says from the case of אישה ishah we see that
even if there's nothing to show that,
you know, in the end we say you've reconciled yourself to it
and it's valid. Okay, now we have to deal with the deeply
disturbing thing that a woman now can be married effectively by a
gun being held to her head. And we already know she can't
be divorced, you know, you know, she has no say in the
divorce, but now that she can be married against her will, I
mean my god, that's given to horrific abuse. All right, so let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. I mean even the case about
the sale and of the field is terrible abuse, but here it's
personal. I mean here it's about, you know, her as a human
being. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. מר בר רב
אשי אמר באישה ודאי קידושין לא הוו. Mar bar Rav Ashi amar
b'ishah vadai kidushin lo havu. No,
you know what, I could agree by other stuff, but by the
case of the woman, when they forced her to say yes, that
is not going to be valid. Even if by a field it
would be, you know, even maybe if they forced him to marry
her, who knows, we could discuss maybe that would be good, but
for her to be forced to be married, that won't be valid.
Why? הוא עשה שלא כהוגן לפיכך עשו עמו שלא כהוגן ואפקיעינהו רבנן
לקידושין מיניה. hu asah shelo khogan lefikach asu imo shelo khogan v'afki'inhu
rabanan l'kidushin minei.
He acted improperly to try to force this woman to marry him,
therefore we're going to act improperly to him and the רבנן rabanan
are going to nullify the קידושין, kidushin, okay? ואפקיעינהו רבנן לקידושין מיניה,
v'afki'inhu rabanan l'kidushin minei, we're not going to recognize the קידושין kidushin
and it's going to be... invalid. So this is the power of
חז"ל Chazal to do הפקעת קידושין, hafkaat kiddushin, to refuse to recognize,
to annul a marriage. Now, how do they have that power? So
that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. So the
גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar leh Ravina le-Rav
Ashi, so this is classic every time the גמרא Gemara says הפקעת
קידושין hafkaat kiddushin you have the following exchange. Said רבינא Ravina to
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, תינח דקדש בכספא, קדש בביאה מאי איכא למימר?
Teinach de-kadesh be-chaspa, kadesh be-viah mai ika le-meimar? I get if he
married her with money, then I can understand the mechanism חז"ל Chazal
used because they could say הפקר בית דין הפקר, hefker beit din
hefker, and we'll make the money ownerless and it wasn't his money
and therefore the קידושין kiddushin wasn't valid. But how what if he
was מקדש בביאה? mekadesh be-viah? How there are we going to be
able to nullify the קידושין? kiddushin? So, by the way, some say,
רש"י, Rashi, רשב"ם, Rashbam רמב"ם, whatever, there's an opinion out there that
קידושי כסף kiddushei chesef is only דרבנן de-rabbanan and קידושי ביאה kiddushei
viah is דאורייתא. de-oraita. So some want to, everybody sort of yells
against that, but for those who say it they want to read
that into this גמרא. Gemara קידושי כסף, kiddushei chesef, that's דרבנן, de-rabbanan,
we can understand how it could nullify it, how could we nullify
קידושי ביאה? kiddushei viah? But normally the difference is not דרבנן de-rabbanan
or דאורייתא. de-oraita. It's understood that both are דאורייתא. de-oraita. But the
question is, we understand how we can manipulate things with money, but
the actual act of ביאה viah we can't say that it didn't
happen and how do we therefore not make it קידושין? kiddushin? So
the גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה שויוהו רבנן לבעילתו בעילת זנות. Amar
leh shavinhu rabbanan le-vilato beilat zenut. Yes,
the rabbis made it into an act of fornication, not an act
of marriage. What does this mean?
So תוספות Tosafot says, so there's three different opinions. The רשב"ם says,
or three ways. כל המקדש אדעתא דרבנן מקדש. kol ha-mekadesh adaita de-rabbanan
mekadesh.
Everybody wants to get married according to what חז"ל Chazal want, so
it's like א תנאי, a tnai, and since in the end חז"ל
Chazal? didn't want it, then deep down you didn't want it either.
Which is pretty funny. What do you mean אדעתא דרבנן מקדש? adaita
de-rabbanan mekadesh? Here he is, he's doing something violent and immoral, how
could we say that but he really wants to do it according
to חז"ל? Chazal So that's what תוספות Tosafot says. תוספות Tosafot says,
points out that often we do use the phrase כל המקדש אדעתא
דרבנן מקדש, kol ha-mekadesh adaita de-rabbanan mekadesh, but it makes no sense
here, because that's when the guy did the right thing at the
time and then retroactively we want to annul the קידושין, kiddushin, so
we say it's like he always implicitly stipulated that it would be
based on whether we חז"ל Chazal would be okay with it, and
therefore we're going to retroactively say it was no good. That works
retroactively when it was good at the
time. You could say that he wanted to do it אדעתא דרבנן.
adaita de-rabbanan. Here the גמרא Gemara does not use the phrase אדעתא
דרבנן, adaita de-rabbanan, and you can't say it's אדעתא דרבנן adaita de-rabbanan
because clearly he's doing it in violation of the will of the
rabbis. He's doing something immoral. So that's why תוספות says the גמרא
Gemara does not use that phrase. It says so what is the
mechanism then? So תוספות says the mechanism is יש כח ביד חכמים
לעקור דבר מן התורה, yesh koach be-yad chachamim la-akor davar min ha-Torah,
that when חז"ל Chazal want to do something they have the power
just to sort of say we override. What exactly that power is,
what does it mean? Does it mean up in heaven this woman
is a married woman but חז"ל Chazal are telling you ignore that?
Somehow חז"ל Chazal the תורה gives them the ability to just nullify
דאורייתא de-oraita realities. But that is יש כח ביד חכמים לעקור דבר
מן התורה. yesh koach be-yad chachamim la-akor davar min ha-Torah. A third
possibility is to
understand that marriage is a social construct. So while this has the
weakness that it does not have him doing it אדעתא דרבנן adaita
de-rabbanan because he's clearly
willingly doing it against what חז"ל want, it has the benefit for
our desire to nullify it, that at the time he is acting
in a way that is demonstrably unacceptable and immoral, עשה שלא כהוגן.
asah shelo ke-hogen. So what it could mean is שויוהו רבנן לבעילתו
בעילת זנות shavinhu rabbanan le-vilato beilat zenut is we as a society
refuse to see this as a marriage. We see this as fornication,
we see this as rape, right? Because of the way he's acting,
it is not קידושי ביאה. kiddushei viah. For it to be contextualized
as קידושי ביאה kiddushei viah that requires not just what's in his
mind but that there's a societal context that can see it that
way and therefore we refuse to see it that way, it's בעילת
זנות. beilat zenut. So that's why it does not work. So even
if תליוהו וזבין talyuhu ve-zavin works with שדה זו sadeh zo and
without counting money and with all that whole stuff, but it would
not work in this case because of הוא עשה שלא כהוגן. hu
asah shelo ke-hogen. So now let's see what the גמרא says. Where
are we? טבי תלה לפפי אקידרא. Tavi tala le-Papi a-kidra.
So טבי Tavi suspended, like coerced this person פפי Papi for a
קידרא kidra which is some type of a tree, some say on
a tree or forced to sell the tree, וזבין, and he sold
it. חתם רבה בר בר חנה אמודעא ואאשקלתא. Chatam Rabbah bar bar
Chana a-mudaa ve-a-ashkelta.
So רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana signed on the
מודעא. mudaa. So now ברוך השם, baruch Hashem, the only sort of
remedy to this idea that this sale is good even if coerced
is that you have the opportunity to write a מודעא. If you
know you're being coerced, you can go to עדים edim and say
I want you to know I'm being coerced, I'm going to say
I'm going along with it but I am not reconciling myself to
it and I am telling you. that I am being coerced and
they sign a document where you declared you were coerced, and then
in that case the sale will not be good. We had this
before about the writing of a מודעה. moda'ah. So anyway, so in
this case רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana signed the
מודעה moda'ah when פפי Papi said I'm being coerced—I mean of course
even the idea of the ability to write a מודעה moda'ah assumes
that you can get away from the situation of coercion, it's not
all happening on the spot, and find witnesses and give them and
be מוסר מודעה. moseir moda'ah. But okay. Anyway so he signed that,
and then he signed also the document of sale. אשקלתא ashkaltah somehow
means the document of sale that happened later. אמר רב הונא: Amar
Rav Huna: מאן דחתים אמודעה שפיר חתים ומאן דחתים אאשקלתא שפיר חתים.
man dechatim amoda'ah shapir chatim uman dechatim a-ashkaltah shapir chatim. The one
who signed on the מודעה moda'ah did well, and the one who
signed on the bill of sale did well. Each one was legitimate.
So the גמרא says: what do you mean each one was legitimate?
One of them is right and one of them isn't. So the
גמרא says like this: מאן דחתים אאשקלתא שפיר חתים? man dechatim a-ashkaltah
shapir chatim? The guy who signed on the bill of sale was
legitimate? ממה נפשך, mimmah nafshach, make up your mind. אם מודעה לא
אשקלתא: im moda'ah lo ashkaltah: if the מודעה moda'ah existed and you
signed a מודעה moda'ah then the bill of sale was not legitimate
because it undermined the bill of sale. ואשקלתא לא מודעה: ve'ashkaltah lo
moda'ah: and if you think the bill of sale is legitimate then
you shouldn't be signing the מודעה. moda'ah. הכי קאמר: Hachi ka'amar: so
the גמרא says fine this is what it means to say. אילב
מודעה מאן דחתים אאשקלתא שפיר חתים: ilav moda'ah man dechatim a-ashkaltah shapir
chatim: were it not for the מודעה moda'ah
then it would have been good, meaning now you know the גמרא
does not seem to be faulting him that he signed both. Okay
you know somehow he was in a situation maybe he couldn't get
out of it or whatever. I mean it's interesting, is it עדות
שקר eidus sheker to sign something? No because you know that person
at that moment is saying that he's selling the field even though
you know that he's expressed his מודעה moda'ah before. So the גמרא
actually isn't faulting him for signing both but it is clear that
once you sign the מודעה moda'ah it neutralizes the bill of sale.
But the גמרא is saying is were you not to have signed
the מודעה moda'ah you would have been okay signing the bill of
sale even though it was coerced. Why would you have been okay
signing a coerced bill of sale? Because רב הונא לטעמיה Rav Huna
l'taimei דאמר רב הונא: de'amar Rav Huna: תליוהו וזבין זביניה זבינא
which brings us to a
perfect closure of what we said before. This is exactly רב הונא's
point that even though it's coerced it's valid so the sale by
itself would have been valid and if you would have just signed
you know that sale it would have been a valid sale. You
also now want to go ahead and sign the מודעה moda'ah you
also are entitled to do that. The person who is coerced is
entitled to say I'm being coerced and I want you to know
I'm not reconciling myself to it and I'm giving a מודעה moda'ah
which neutralizes it which at least there has the benefit of at
least being a possible sort of neutralizer of all of this. Of
course the problem
is as תוספות discusses this then what happens if at the sale
you say I'm מבטל mevatel any מודעה moda'ah that I might have
made? You know then we've closed off the escape hatch. And what
happens? Like it gets infinite regress. Can you say at the מודעה
moda'ah when you're making the מודעה moda'ah this is a מודעה moda'ah
and
I'm protesting that I don't agree even when I'm going to say
I'm מבטל מודעה mevatel moda'ah I'm not being מבטל mevatel this? Like
which one of those wins out? But you know it's sort of
like what they do with viruses and anti-viruses you're always trying to
stay one step ahead. But the problem here is obviously it's a
problematic situation that coercion will be good and there will be no
way of actually getting out of it if you can have ביטול
מודעה. bitul moda'ah. But at least now in the גמרא we're not
mentioning ביטול מודעה, bitul moda'ah, מודעה moda'ah at least is a way
that you can ultimately protect yourself if that's available. Okay we'll stop
here.